SELWYN McCRACKEN, Ph.D.

I am a Ph.D. qualified data scientist with extensive experience at applying classical and innovative statistical techniques across the Financial Services, Government, Pharmaceutical, Healthcare, Automotive and Consumer Goods sectors.

A portfolio of examples is available on my website http://selwyn-mccracken.com

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Ernst and Young - Fraud Investigation and Dispute Services (London) Data Analytics Manager, October 2011 – September 2012.

I co-managed a team of 6 - 10 data analysts at the heart of Ernst & Young's largest global project, which aims to improve the public finances of a sub-Saharan African Government.

My principal role was to lead and coordinate the analytical support my team provided to the 200+ E&Y business analysts and forensic accountants that are assisting across a range of Government activities such as Budget, Revenue, Expenditure, Debt Management, IT & HR.

Examples of specific activities that I led include:

- Implementation of an interactive web-based visualisation and financial reporting portal;
- Diagnosis of system integration issues across the key Government databases;
- Design, review and validation of predictive models (e,g, identifying Ministries that will overspend their budget);
- Reconciliation of external debt disbursements and repayments, across the various debt monitoring systems;
- Tax payment and fine monitoring of companies granted tax breaks and exemptions;
- Quality assurance reviews and code version control processes for all requests

Ernst and Young - Fraud Investigation and Dispute Services (London) Data Analytics Executive, March 2010 – September 2011

Completed several pieces of work on E&Y's largest project such as:

- Tracing and visualisation of \$8.5 Billion of tax revenue through more than 200 taxation accounts
- Confirmation of \$5 Billion of suspected outstanding payments to Government vendors
- Account reconciliation and fuzzy transaction matching between the Government's financial system and commercial bank account statements
- Clustering of Ministries according to budget and expenditure behaviour to identify high variance outliers
- Hadoop-based large-scale parallel computation analysis proof of concept trial
- · Automatic classification of financial system transactions from free-text descriptions in SQL

Vanguard Strategy (London)

Senior Analyst, January 2008 - February 2010

Provided statistical support on client engagements, research design, and presented results to clients. Major client engagements included:

Continental tyres (Germany, UK, Czech Republic) – Tyre market consumer dynamics:

- Established the main drivers of tyre purchases for the client brand, brand loyalty, and the development of brand preference using logistic regression modelling.
- Estimated customer lifetime value via survival analysis (adjusting for car purchasing behaviour, preference decay and brand switching patterns).
- Forecasted market share equilibria of tyre channels

Wyeth Pharmaceuticals (UK) – Effexor (antidepressant) end-of-life sales force reallocation

• Saved £1.75m in salary and support costs by optimising the size of a Pharmaceutical sales force across geographic regions and product line, after taking into consideration drug lifecycles, promotional effectiveness, intensity, and affordability of sales reps.

Coca Cola (Japan) – Georgia coffee:

• Established that Coke Japan were incorrectly targeting canned coffee consumers that were 10-15 years older than the bulk of their customer base, thus potentially alienating the younger consumers required to maintain the longer term viability of their coffee range

Vanguard Strategy (London)

Analyst-Statistician, June 2006 – December 2007:

• Identified high-value Physician segments within the US Anti-Depressant market.

- Identified early adopters of a new Anti-Depressant drug based on past analogue uptake.
- Estimated the level of influence that a Specialist has upon their linked GPs prescribing behaviour.

Dept. Preventive & Social Medicine, University of Otago (New Zealand) Health Research Council Training Fellow, April 2001-December 2005:

- Undertook PhD Research, epidemiology tutoring, supervisor research assistance, and Public Health training
- PhD research focused on the design and analysis of a national injury statistics database for the New Zealand construction industry, requiring:
 - Regression based analysis of construction injury risk factors and injury rate fluctuations over time.
 - Machine-learning classification of free-text injury descriptions.

Dept. Preventive & Social Medicine, University of Otago (New Zealand) Junior Research Fellow. 1999-2001

- Identified risk factors for Fatal Work Related Injuries amongst Maori Workers.
- Established that fatality rate differences for Maori & Non-Maori workers is due to occupational concentration.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Expert user of the $\underline{\mathbf{R}}$ programming language:

- Multivariate regression modelling and prediction (linear & logistic regression).
- Tree-based segmentation and classification (e.g. random-forests)
- Loyalty/Survival/Time-to-Event modelling
- Machine Learning classification & pattern recognition (SVMs, kNN, kmeans)
- Data cleaning, missing-data interpolation and imputation
- Monte-Carlo and bootstrap analyses, kernel density estimation
- Advanced interactive graphics e.g. multi-dimensional plots, map making and plot animation
- Time series analysis and forecasting

Seasoned **SQL** database analyst:

• PostgreSQL, MS SQL Server, MySQL, MS-Access, SQLite.

'Big Data' tools experience with **Hadoop**:

- Hadoop cluster deployment on Amazon's EC2 with Apache Whirr.
- Mahout machine learning library.
- Pig.

Interactive web-based data visualisation skills:

- D3.js.
- JQuery + Javascript.

Considerable **Python** programming experience:

- Scripting, analysis automation, database ETL, data cleaning, & text processing (including XML).
- Compilation of standalone executables (py2exe)
- Automated MS PPT & Word report generation (win32com)
- Hardware interfacing (pyserial)

Capable **Linux** user and administrator (primarily the Debian and Ubuntu distros):

- Shell scripting and task automation
- Remote access and cluster computing configuration (e.g. initiating a Hadoop cluster via SSH on Amazon EC2)
- Git version control

EDUCATION

2007 Ph.D. – Occupational Epidemiology. University of Otago (New Zealand)

2001 MSc - Psychology, University of Otago

1999 BSc - Psychology, University of Otago

PERSONAL DETAILS

Nationality: New Zealand

UK Work Visa: Tier 1 General (Have just applied for Indefinite Leave to Remain)
Email: selwyn.mccracken@gmail.com

Mobile: (+44) 789-686-9183

Website: http://selwyn-mccracken.com